<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[My Octopress Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://akbarbmirza.github.io/blog/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://akbarbmirza.github.io/blog/"/>
  <updated>2015-08-15T18:21:44-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://akbarbmirza.github.io/blog/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Your Name]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First Post]]></title>
    <link href="http://akbarbmirza.github.io/blog/blog/2015/08/10/first-post/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-10T16:41:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://akbarbmirza.github.io/blog/blog/2015/08/10/first-post</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Markdown GO!</h2>

<p>OMG! I have a <em>real</em> blog now!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to My Blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://akbarbmirza.github.io/blog/blog/2015/06/19/welcome-to-my-blog/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-19T16:30:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://akbarbmirza.github.io/blog/blog/2015/06/19/welcome-to-my-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>YWeb, Cohort 2, Week 1</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s been in an interesting week. This was the first week of the YWeb Career
Academy program. It&rsquo;s been really exciting and I&rsquo;ve met so many different kinds
of people here hoping to learn web development. It&rsquo;s inspiring to hear the
stories of the people around me and their motivations for learning how to code.
This will be the first post in a long line of posts about the program and
my thoughts.</p>

<p>While the roll out of the laptops wasn&rsquo;t as smooth as we hoped, we were all
eventually able to start. We talked about the Terminal (Shell) and basic
commands there, as well as Markdown and the basics of using Git and Github. I
learned a lot and was able to offer my help to the students who have less
experience and do my best to help explain some of the new concepts that they&rsquo;re
facing. It&rsquo;s also a little difficult because the backgrounds and prior
experience with computers is so diverse.</p>

<p>I think something that would help make the YWeb program more successful, is some
form of pre-work that ensures that all the students have the same base computer
skills (and if they don&rsquo;t, helps them get them so that they can follow along).
Resources like these are insanely valuable, and incredibly important, especially
when coding.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s it for this week. See you next time!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
