<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Yweb | My Octopress Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://akbarbmirza.github.io/blog/blog/categories/yweb/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://akbarbmirza.github.io/blog/"/>
  <updated>2015-08-15T20:32:19-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://akbarbmirza.github.io/blog/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Your Name]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Post-Drifty Visit and Code School Front End]]></title>
    <link href="http://akbarbmirza.github.io/blog/blog/2015/07/24/week-six/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-24T16:30:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://akbarbmirza.github.io/blog/blog/2015/07/24/week-six</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>YWeb, Cohort 2, Week 6</h2>

<p>Plenty to talk about this week. This week was largely a work-week as opposed
to a work-learn week. Last Friday, we visited Drifty, which was pretty cool.
This week, we continued working through Chapter 03 in EloquentJS, talked about
taking care of ourselves and started working on our portfolios.</p>

<h3>Drifty Visit</h3>

<p>The visit to Drifty was a pretty cool experience. We went to a tech talk about
the Ionic Framework (a framework to help make hybrid web applications using
the web stack) and Firebase (a super awesome tool that makes databases easy
for web apps). I&rsquo;ve played around with Ionic before and had a lot of fun
with it, so I&rsquo;m excited to check it out again. Firebase seems like it&rsquo;ll be
really awesome to build complex web apps much quicker because I don&rsquo;t have
to worry about a database as much.</p>

<p>The Drifty Office was nice and spacious. There was a lot of natural lighting
and it seems like a very chilled out place to work. It was refreshing to hear
that Ionic was very flexible in terms of working remotely and working where
you want, and I hope that some of the other tech companies we visit follow
that same philosophy.</p>

<h3>EloquentJS - Chapter 03</h3>

<p>Chapter 03 has been the toughest chapter yet for a couple of reasons. There
are interesting, more complex topics like Recursion and Closure that take time
and effort to wrap your head around. There were also a couple of issues with
the workbook because exercises and tests take much longer to create than they
take to do.</p>

<p>It was an eye-opening week because we learned about all the different things
that could happen when working on a deadline, as well as common mistakes that
all developers make. We learned how to spot them and how to fix them, and I
think it has made us all better programmers.</p>

<h3>Code School - Front End Formations, CSS Cross Country</h3>

<p>This week in Code School, I completed the Front End Formations and CSS Cross
Country courses. CSS Cross Country was helpful in terms of learning more
advanced CSS topics such as clearing, pseudo-selectors, and CSS specificity.
However, the cheesiness of many of the videos and the lesson clearly being of
their earlier courses made it a less enjoyable ride. The information was
important but there could definitely be better ways of teaching that
knowledge. The Front End Formations course was very useful in terms of
learning what&rsquo;s new in HTML 5 and CSS 3 and making sure that we know when and
how to use newer elements and properties.</p>

<h3>Mental Health &amp; Meditating</h3>

<p>We talked about mental health and self care on Thursday. We learned that the
number of people who suffer from mental health in Tech is pretty high and that
it&rsquo;s very important that we take steps to make sure that we&rsquo;re taking care of
ourselves and have a foundation to keep ourselves in check. We also talked
about meditation and how it&rsquo;s a good way to relax and kind of re-center
yourself. I mentioned the website <a href="http://calm.com">Calm.com</a> in class. It&rsquo;s a
pretty useful tool that lets you set a time, and either go through a guided
meditation or listen to ambient noise to help you meditate.</p>

<h3>Portfolio Beginnings</h3>

<p>After creating thumbnails and mockups for our portfolio last week, we started
putting our HTML skills to the test. We talked about semantic HTML and started
writing the Semantic HTML Code Skeleton for our portfolios. I&rsquo;m pretty excited
for when we go ahead and start editing the CSS of our pages and bring our
portfolios to life.</p>

<h3>FreeCodeCamp</h3>

<p>After a couple months of hiatus, I&rsquo;ve finally got back on
<a href="http://freecodecamp.com">FreeCodeCamp</a>. FreeCodeCamp is a free online boot
camp that proposes to teach front-end web development concepts. After 800
hours of practice with front-end skills, students jump into real-world
projects with non-profits to hone and develop their skills while doing some
good. A lot has changed since I was on it first and the community has only
gotten more vibrant. I&rsquo;m looking forward to continue working through it.</p>

<h3>New Stress Release</h3>

<p>On Thursday, a group of my friends at YWeb and I started playing a strange
derivate of Taps (think &lsquo;hot potato&rsquo; with a ball, except it never stops unless
someone drops it) during our breaks. It&rsquo;s been an incredibly calming exercise
and it&rsquo;s a nice way to take a break and step away from the work and just have
fun.</p>

<p>Phew! That was a long post. I probably should have split it up, but here we
are.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s it for this week. See you next time!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[CSS Zen Garden and Advanced Selectors]]></title>
    <link href="http://akbarbmirza.github.io/blog/blog/2015/07/24/week-seven/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-24T16:30:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://akbarbmirza.github.io/blog/blog/2015/07/24/week-seven</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>YWeb, Cohort 2, Week 7</h2>

<p>It was an interesting week. We started Chapter 4 in Eloquent JavaScript,
tinkered with CSS Zen Garden and worked on the CSS for our portfolios. We also
started furthering our CSS skills with the Advanced Selectors project.</p>

<h3>EloquentJS - Chapter 04</h3>

<p>Chapter 04 of Eloquent JavaScript was very tough. We learned about Objects and
Arrays, which are awesome. The examples in the book, however, used a lot of
Math that seemed like they were more there to show off the author&rsquo;s knowledge
rather than to explain the concepts illustrated in the chapter. The end of
chapter exercises were still pretty interesting to work with.</p>

<h3>CSS Zen Garden</h3>

<p>Working with the CSS Zen Garden was kind of fun. The creator had made some
interesting choices with the way he structured the HTML so some of our style
decisions were made more difficult because of it. All in all though, it was a
great example of why it&rsquo;s important and even convenient to separate your
content and your design/layout. Floating seems to be one of the iffier
concepts to wrap our heads around as it doesn&rsquo;t always work as expected.</p>

<h3>Portfolio Work</h3>

<p>We continued to work on our portfolios by fleshing out our CSS skeletons for
our personal portfolios. In order to figure out some elements of my layout, I
experimented with CSS Flexbox. Flexbox is intriguing by itself, and being able
to use it as a grid layout is really cool. It&rsquo;s still a little confusing, but
I&rsquo;m getting better at understanding it the more I use it.</p>

<h3>Advanced Selectors Project</h3>

<p>I had a lot of fun with the advanced selectors project, but I can&rsquo;t talk about
it yet. I&rsquo;ll be showing off a demo next week, and I think it&rsquo;ll be pretty
exciting! One thing I learned during the project are that <em>keyframes are
awesome!</em>.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s it for this week. See you next time!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[jQuery & Portfolio Work]]></title>
    <link href="http://akbarbmirza.github.io/blog/blog/2015/07/24/week-eight/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-24T16:30:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://akbarbmirza.github.io/blog/blog/2015/07/24/week-eight</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>YWeb, Cohort 2, Week 8</h2>

<p>It was an interesting week. We continued Chapter 04 in Eloquent JavaScript,
tinkered with jQuery and worked on the final copy and artwork for our
portfolios. We also started our jQuery plugin projects and figuring out what
we&rsquo;re going to do with that.</p>

<h3>EloquentJS - Chapter 04</h3>

<p>Chapter 04 of Eloquent JavaScript has been going pretty smoothly. We initially
ran into some bugs with the Chapter 04 exercises and test files overwriting
those of Chapter 03, but those were resolved pretty quickly. The exercises
themselves have also been pretty interesting. The ones that gave me a little
bit of trouble were the ones having to do with Double Linked Lists. One of the
problems in my approach, that I learned the hard way, is that JavaScript
doesn&rsquo;t let you pass a whole object container by reference. In other words, I
couldn&rsquo;t change the object I passed, whole-hog while in a function. To work
around that, I had to do a little bit of extra work creating a buffer and
moving things around in my object, but it was definitely confusing at first.</p>

<h3>Code School - Try jQuery &amp; JavaScript Best Practices</h3>

<p>We started talking about jQuery this week and I&rsquo;m really excited for it. I&rsquo;ve
gone through Code School&rsquo;s Try jQuery course in the past and I really enjoyed
it, so I was glad that the other students were able to experience it. In the
meantime, I was working on the JavaScript Best Practices course which taught
me a bit about some of the things that happened behind the scenes in
JavaScript. It also showed me how to make simple optimizations when it comes
to loops.</p>

<h3>Portfolio Work - Content</h3>

<p>Working on the portfolio this week was tough. Who knew that writing content
was so tough? It&rsquo;s tough figuring out exactly what I want to say on the
website that other people will see me on. Not to mention figuring out what to
do with the layout elements that I had previously mocked up and created on my
HTML. I&rsquo;m starting to feel better now that I&rsquo;m looking at it more like a Work
in Progress than the final set-in-stone edition, but it&rsquo;s still a little bit
nerve-wracking. I&rsquo;ve added a couple of images and had fun creating flat
buttons for my social media connection links. I&rsquo;ll continue to work on it
throughout the rest of the program and my career, but I feel like it has a
good foundation right now.</p>

<h3>Zendesk</h3>

<p>We&rsquo;re going to go visit Zendesk today, so I&rsquo;m pretty excited about that. I
don&rsquo;t know much about them, but I have experienced their product once through
the Customer Service at OnePlus One. It&rsquo;ll be interesting to hear from them
and see what other tech companies in Madison are like.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s it for this week. See you next time!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Post-Madison+UX and Chapter 03]]></title>
    <link href="http://akbarbmirza.github.io/blog/blog/2015/07/16/week-five/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-16T16:30:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://akbarbmirza.github.io/blog/blog/2015/07/16/week-five</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>YWeb, Cohort 2, Week 5</h2>

<p>This week we started hot off the heels of the Madison+UX Conference. We
started the week with a class-wide Code Review where we went over the Chapter
2 Exercises. We started Chapter 03 of JavaScript, and also started learning
about HTML and CSS through Code School. I also kept working on Project Euler.</p>

<h3>Madison+UX</h3>

<p>The Madison+UX Conference was a lot of fun. The swag was cool, but the
presentations were even cooler. We got to listen to great talks about <em>Saving
the Floppy Disk</em> and <em>Generation Z</em>. We also heard about different ways to
think about User Experience, and Chris Coyier (of CodePen) gave a great
presentation (with lots of flashy demos) on SVG. Being around so many
different developers and designers was an amazing experience. I&rsquo;m kind of sad
to hear that this is the last Madison+UX conference, but I&rsquo;m sure the
community will continue to embrace the spirit of the conference in future
events.</p>

<h3>Code Review</h3>

<p>This week, we saw what Code Review actually looks like. We got some hands-on
experience with Code Review by going over the Chapter 02 Workbook for Eloquent
JavaScript. It was interesting to see all the different ways we solved our
problems. Although the process of reviewing code was a bit clunky, I learned a
lot during the review and I&rsquo;m sure the other students have as well.</p>

<h3>EloquentJS Chapter 03</h3>

<p>We went over Chapter 03 of EloquentJS this week, which covers functions in
JavaScript. I&rsquo;m pretty familiar with functions in JavaScript and other
languages, but the one concept that I always have trouble wrapping my head
around are closures. I&rsquo;m familiar with some of the concepts and benefits of
them, including isolating an environment and being able to curry or partially
curry a function, but I think I&rsquo;d need to see several more real-world examples
of closures to grasp them. If anyone has some good suggestions for reading on
Closures, I&rsquo;d be interested in hearing it.</p>

<h3>Project Euler</h3>

<p>I don&rsquo;t have much of a status update about Project Euler this week. I worked
on the Smallest Multiple problem on Project Euler, but I have to go back to
the drawing board and clear up the way I&rsquo;m approaching the problem. I&rsquo;ll look
at it more over the weekend and next week and see how that goes.</p>

<h3>Visit to Drifty</h3>

<p>We&rsquo;ll be visiting Drifty today. I&rsquo;m pretty excited just because I&rsquo;ve seen some
of their workshops on Ionic and their use of Angular.JS to build hybrid web
apps. In fact, I even have some experience with the Ionic framework as I did
some (very basic) work with it while I was working part-time at MobileIgniter.
I look forward to the demos that they&rsquo;ll be doing and seeing what the culture
at Drifty is like. I think it&rsquo;ll be a good way to see what tech culture is
like in Madison.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s it for this week. See you next time!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Basics of Design and Madison+UX Prep]]></title>
    <link href="http://akbarbmirza.github.io/blog/blog/2015/07/09/week-four/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-09T16:30:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://akbarbmirza.github.io/blog/blog/2015/07/09/week-four</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>YWeb, Cohort 2, Week 4</h2>

<p>Phew, what an interesting week. Between working out the origins of our group
the {Curly Braces}, making silly (i.e. corny) science puns, learning the
basics of design, and working through Project Euler, it was a busy week. Let&rsquo;s
start at the beginning.</p>

<h3>The {Curly Braces}</h3>

<p>The {Curly Braces} is the name of our squad in the YWebCA program. We&rsquo;ve
started working on the details and our mission, but so far it&rsquo;s just a bunch
of us who get lunch together, make silly puns and jokes, and are working hard
to get through the program. We&rsquo;re thinking of getting t-shirts that say:</p>

<blockquote><p>At first there was <strong>Φ</strong>, then there was the <strong>{Curly Braces}</strong></p></blockquote>

<p>We&rsquo;re still working on our design and stuff but we&rsquo;re growing pretty quick.
We&rsquo;ve got our own <code>#slack</code> group and the only way to go from here is up.</p>

<h3>Design Workshop</h3>

<p>On Wednesday, we did a design workshop where we went over some of the basic elements and principles of design. We touched on a few topics, more than I could probably detail in this post, which is already getting pretty long, so I&rsquo;ll leave that for another day. In the meantime, I&rsquo;ll tease you with this table.</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th style="text-align:center;"> Elements </th>
<th style="text-align:center;"> Principles  </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center;"> Line     </td>
<td style="text-align:center;"> Balance     </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center;"> Shape    </td>
<td style="text-align:center;"> Contrast    </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center;"> Form     </td>
<td style="text-align:center;"> Focal Point </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center;"> Space    </td>
<td style="text-align:center;"> Harmony     </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center;"> Color    </td>
<td style="text-align:center;"> Movement    </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center;"> Value    </td>
<td style="text-align:center;"> Repetition  </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center;"> Texture  </td>
<td style="text-align:center;"> Proportion  </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td style="text-align:center;">          </td>
<td style="text-align:center;"> Variety     </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<h3>Project Euler</h3>

<p>After finishing Part III of the <em>JavaScript Road Trip</em> on Code School, I
wanted to work on something else. Nate gave me an assignment to build a prime
number generator, which was a nice exercise. Afterwards, Annalise suggested
that we check out Project Euler if we wanted some more challenges. I checked
it out and it was pretty awesome. I finished the first two challenges pretty
quickly, but then got stumped on the third, which had to do with finding the
largest prime factorization of a very large number. I had a solution but
because it was a brute-force solution and the number was so large, the
computer had to churn to get the result. I wasn&rsquo;t that patient and so after
picking Annalise&rsquo;s brain and struggling through the problem, I ended up trying
a lazy solution to the problem, by finding the first pair of factors that I
could, and finding the prime factorization of those. This also took a little
while because one of the factors was very large, but smaller by at least an
order of 10. When I finally got the result, I was so satisfied.</p>

<p>As for the silly pun, think about this:</p>

<blockquote><p>The Bible says <em>&ldquo;Adam &amp; Eve&rdquo;</em>, not <em>&ldquo;Atom &amp; Electron&rdquo;</em></p></blockquote>

<p>Excuse the corniness.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s it for this week. See you next time!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
